Let's move now on to the
file system structure. So how is a file system
organizing different layers.
The idea when you design a file system is
to have different layers for different functionalities.
This is true for a file system, but I even
mentioned this in the very beginning of the
course for the entire operating system that
you can have different layers. It's good for
modularity and keeping
let's say different types of jobs in different
levels / in different models, so these are
basically the different layers you can have
if you want to organize your file system in
let's say different parts, so you need the
lowest one so the one that is very close to
the device to be about I/O control. You
will need a part of the file system that is
the one that actually
speaks this kind of language, which is read
a specific drive, maybe a specific cylinder
and track. This is of course for a rotating
disk, it doesn't apply to an SSD, but it's the
very low level IO layer that speaks basically
the language of the device.
On top of that, you have the basic file system
so called basic file system. It speaks in
terms of blocks, so it says retrieve a specific
block or write to a specific block and it's
also the one that maintains buffers and caches,
when you read and write to the disk, these
are similar in spirit to what we discussed
also for
the memory.
You have the file organization module and
this is about translating logical blocks into
physical blocks. So if you want to read the
fifth block of a file again to simplify the
life of the programmer the processes and
so on, the operating system separates between
logical and physical addresses, so
from the logical perspective, the fifth block
is the fifth block. It starts at 0, so it
will be blocked #4, but in practice this *file*
might be written in a disk in several
position. The disk is not going to use
necessarily contiguous allocation, and I will
present this in the next video.
In this layer you also have the managing of
free space, so not only the translation between
logical and physical, but also this is the layer
that maintains information about where you
can actually write if you need to write something
new.
And here, of course, you start having understanding
of files too, not only blocks because
of course you need to
have the concept of a file in order to understand
what is the logical block inside that file
and translate that into the physical one.
The highest one, the highest level you have just before
actually the applications that you run,
is the logical file system. This is where
we keep all the metadata I introduced before
And now this is what we are going to discuss
next when we see at different ways of actually
maintaining
stuff (data/files) into the disk.
Before that I also want to mention that since
you have this separation of functionalities
in different layers, this is what allows you
to have virtual file systems. So in practice
you can have
different file systems that are maintained
at the same time and they can be implemented
in different ways. Maybe speaking to different
type of devices and so on. Since you have
the different layers you can define also a layer
that is the virtual file system which does
once again
acts as a middleware. Stays in between the
lower level interfaces and the higher ones,
the user, the processes,
to translate commands like open a file read a
file and so on from the general interface,
the common shared interface with the user
to the specific ones you have for each file
system.
The next thing we're going to look at in the
next video, it's how we actually implement
files. How do we keep them? If we have
a disk block n on our device,
how do we know
what is the file that is contained on that
block? We will discuss three different
ways, contiguous allocation, linked list
allocation also with the file allocation table
variant and I-nodes that are the ones you
actually use, for example, in your Unix
systems.